A Guide to the Percy Wallace MacKaye Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7431-a
Percy Wallace MacKaye Collection 1897-1948
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7431-a
12 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to reseaarch.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [17 December 1963] 24 March 1965
Item Listing
- Manuscript
  - Fair copy of two stanzas from "Moments en Voyage": poem for the Harvard Class of 1897, n. d.; AMsS 1 p.
- Letters
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Richard Watson Gilder, 1906 June 29; ALS 2 p.
    [Asks Gilder to write something for
    The Century
    on MacKaye's play
    Shappho and Phaon
    starring Julia Marlowe and E. H. Sothern; mentions color sketches of the actors made by Barry Faulkner; MacKaye mentions that he is working on another play, "Jeanne d'Arc", scheduled for October; mentions that
    Sappho and Phaon
    is scheduled to open December 10, 1906 in Chicago, and that MacMillan will publish the play; mentions William Vaughn Moody. ]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Walter Prichard Eaton, 1908 Jan 10; TLS w/env 1 p.
    [Letter discusses a lunch appointment with Eaton, drama critic for
    The [New York] Morning Sun
    . ]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Mr. Browne, 1914 Oct 24; ALS 4 p.
    [Discusses the stage and the technical aspects of the marionette performance of
    Pageant and Masque of St. Louis
    given in May. States that accounts of the production can be found in July or August
    World's Work
    by Prof. George Pierce Baker, in the August
    Review of Reviews
    by Arthur Farwell, and the Sept.
    Current Literature
    . Estimates that 1/2 million people saw the performances.]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Charles D. Scott, 1925 Nov 29; ALS 1 p. [Note written on an envelope]
    [The note was enclosed with an autographed photo (the photo is not in this collection). Says the plays he likes best are:
    A Garland to Sylvia
    ,
    This Fine Pretty World
    , and
    The Scarecrow
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Hamilton Bowen Holt, 1926 Feb 21; ALS 1 p.
    [Offers sympathy to Holt on a great loss.]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Roy Day(?), 1928 Aug 10; ALS 1 p.
    [Discusses the proof of a book by Ernest Harold Baynes and requests extra copies for Baynes' widow and friends.]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Walter Prichard Eaton, 1929 Feb 18; ALS 1 p.
    [Encloses a book by Dartmouth Press which contains Eaton's greeting at MacKaye's 50th birthday celebration. At the invitation of Hamilton Holt he is spending a few weeks at Rollins College to meet with students interested in poetry.]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Carty Ranck, 1931 March 22; APCS
    [Thanks Ranck for the birthday greeting and wishes his new play success. Mentions that he is lecturing in Florida. Written on a picture post card with a scene of a highway through orange groves near Winter Park, Florida. ]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Walter Prichard Eaton, 1932 Feb 15; ALS w/env 2 p.
    [Sends Eaton a copy of
    Wakefield
    for review in a New York newspaper. Extends an invitation to Eaton to attend the Washington, D. C. premiere on Feb. 21 to which the President, Cabinet, Supreme Court, Ambassadors, and Congress have been invited.]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to Louis Untermeyer, 1941 Mar 6; TLS 3 p.
    [Mentions meeting Untermeyer at a National Institute of Arts and Letters meeting; MacKaye sends him four books by MacKaye that were published in Europe:
    The Far Familiar
    In Another Land
    Poesia Religio
    My Lady Dear, Arise
    discusses publication in pre-World War II and inter-World War II Europe. ]
  - Percy Wallace MacKaye to [William (?)] Maxwell, n. d.; ANS 1. p
    [Discusses an article MacKaye has agreed to write about Santa Claus.]
    [Note: Correspondent is identified as (William) Maxwell because he was editor of
    The New Yorker
    Reader's Guide to Periodical Literature
    lists several articles by Percy Wallace MacKaye published in
    . However, an article about Santa is not listed.]